# 把这三种辣椒都放下去一起炒
Stir-fry the three kinds of chili pepper together
# 这叫三合一
This is 'three in one'
# 所以川菜讲究味道
So Sichuan food dedicates to good flavor
# 非常香 看着就好
Very aromatic. It's already good from its look
# 你说香不香
Delicious, isn't it?
# 国辉 师父好 师叔好
-Guohui. -Hello, master and Shishu (Junior master, here it means Er Bai)
# 重庆小面虽然叫小面
Chongqing Xiao Mian, though literally means 'Small Noodles'
# 但是它有大智慧
It contains great wisdom
# 因为这个小面主要就是
Because basically, the Xiao Mian relies on
# 一个辣椒和麻椒的一个组合
the combination of chili pepper and Sichuan peppercorns
# 好的麻椒一定是川椒 碧绿的青的
The best peppercorns must be from Sichuan. Green ones
# 把它粉碎了 不用炒也不用炸 直接生的
Grind it.  No need to stir-fry or fry. Use raw.
# 因为生的麻椒它的香味出不来
Raw Sichuan peppercorn doesn't fully release its aroma
# 一定要经过热油高温的处理它才出香味
It must be processed with high-temperature oil to give the aroma
# 如果家里面有菜籽油是最好
It'd be best if you have rapeseed oil
# 油的温度应该是在
The temperature of the oil should be...
# 一百二到一百五十度左右 也就是五成
between 120 and 150 degrees Celcius, or '50% hot'
# 搁这儿吧要不然烫着
Put it down. Don't get burnt
# 你看油呲进去 冒的是油花儿
See? When the hot oil goes in, bubbles go up
#这里我觉得'油花'指的应该是花椒中本来含有的芳香油在热油的温度下沸腾造成的泡泡
# 产生的麻椒的香味 太香了
That gives the aroma. So fragrant
# 辣椒先炒一下
Stir-fry the chili pepper first
# 小火慢慢的先炒 小点火
Stir-fry it slowly. Lower the heat
# 把这三种辣椒都放下去一起炒
Stir-fry the three kinds of chili pepper together
# 子弹头 二斤条 灯笼椒
'Zidantou', 'Erjingtiao', and 'Denglongjiao' chili peppers
# 炒的时候一定火要小一点 离火
You must use low heat while frying. Or just move the wok away from the heater
# 如果火大的话 辣椒容易糊
If the heat is too powerful, the chili peppers will be burnt
# 辣椒炒的颜色微微红就可以了
It's done when the chili turns dark red
# 炒好了之后粉碎一下
Grind it after stir-frying
# 这三种辣椒味道更厚重
The mixture of three types of chili gives a thick flavor
# 所以川菜讲究味道
Sichuan food dedicates to good flavor
# 炸辣椒油的话五成油温就差不多了
To make chili oil, 50% hot (150 degrees Celcius) is ok
# 先倒一点点油 先试一下温度
Pour a little oil first to test the temperature
# 如果油温过高的话
If the oil temperature is too high
# 那么炸出来辣椒会发苦 它不香
The chili peppers will be bitter, instead of aromatic
# 如果凉了香味激不出来
Otherwise, if the temperature is too low, the aroma will not be released
# 我们炸辣椒油
While preparing the chili oil
# 不光炸辣椒 这里还备点芝麻
Not only the chili pepper. Prepare some sesame as well
# 炸到芝麻微微的变色就可以了
Fry the sesame till the color changes a bit
# 炸至金黄色
Until it looks golden
# 你说重庆小面能不好吃吗
Chongqing Xiao Mian can't taste bad in this way
# 豆瓣酱是四川的郫县豆瓣酱是最好的
Doubanjiang from Pixian, Sichuan is the best
# 因为它比较粗一点
Since it's a bit coarse
# 那么我们简单的把它稍微剁一下
Let's mince it
# 豆瓣是用胡豆 辣椒 面粉做的
Doubanjiang is made from broad bean, chili pepper, and flour
# 所以把剁碎一点点 大家记住了啊
So we need to mince it. Remember this point!
# 小面它有翘头
Xiao Mian has some toppings
# 选普通的肥瘦肉就行
We can just choose normal fat and lean pork
# 我们先下豆瓣酱 把豆瓣酱炒香
First stir-fry the Doubanjiang until aromatic
# 火小一点 把豆瓣的香味
Use low heat to bring out its aroma
# 和它的颜色炒出来
and its color
# 豆瓣酱在四川和重庆那边
Doubanjiang, in Sichuan and Chongqing
# 是家家户户有的
in Sichuan and Chongqing
# 我老婆是重庆潼南人
My wife is from Tongnan, Chongqing
# 丈母娘家那边每次都是
Her family uses their home-made Doubanjiang to cook for us
# 自己家酿的豆瓣给我们炒菜
every time when we visit them
# 吃完了之后我们还得带点回家
We also bring some with us after visiting
# 尤其自己家里做的（最好了）
Home-made Doubanjiang is the best
# 然后把肉末下下去把它煸炒香
Then put the minced meat into the wok and stir-fry
# 你看国辉这个炒馅 炒这个还不一样
See? Guohui is cooking the meat in a different way
# 他是先炒酱后炒肉
He stir-fries the Doubanjiang first, then the meat
# 也就是说能把豆瓣酱炒的特别香
In this way, the Doubanjiang can be very aromatic
# 同样的肉就是你做为什么香
That's the reason why you can make the meat smell good
# 可能换个人做的有点腥
while someone else may retain the bad odor
# 我们煸馅儿的时候
When stir-frying the minced meat
# 一定要把肉的水分要煸出去
We must dry out the moisture
# 要煸香再下料
Add other ingredients after it smells good
# 放一点点料酒去腥就可以
Add some Chinese cooking wine to remove the odor
# 最好用前肩肉稍微肥瘦均匀
We'd better use pork shoulder, which gives a balanced fat/lean ratio
# 而且它的肉质纤维没有那么粗
Also, the muscle fiber of this part is relatively fine
# 看到了吧 重庆小面一步二步三步
See? Step-by-step to make Chongqing Xiao Mian
# 每一步都特别精细 锅洗一下
Each step is very meticulous. Rinse the wok now
# 下一步把豌豆放到高压锅里面去压
Next, boil the peas in a pressure cooker
# 豌豆一定是带皮的
Peas must still have coat with it
# 干的豌豆最少要泡个十个小时以上
The dry peas must be soaked for over 10 hours (before cooking)
# 有电高压锅的最少要压四十分钟
In a pressure cooker, boil the peas for at least 40 minutes
# 今天早上一来我就把豌豆提前就压好了
I've boiled the peas in advance when I came here in the morning
# 大家可以看一下 这是压熟的
Please take a look. These are boiled peas
# 这豌豆特别甜
The peas are very sweet
# 然后这小面还有几种调料
In addition, there are some other ingredients for Xiao Mian
# 芽菜一定要四川宜宾的芽菜是最好的
"Ya Cai" (Sichuan preserved mustard greens), must be from Yibin, Sichuan
# 一定要用水洗一下
You need to wash it with water
# 之后要放锅里面再用油炒一下
Then stir-fry it with oil
# 把芽菜本身的香味给炒出来
To bring out its intrinsic aroma
# 因为时间的关系
Due to the limited time
# 所以我就提前把这个炒出来了
I cooked it in advance
# 接下来做什么
What's next?
# 做小面一定要有姜和蒜
You must also have ginger and garlic to make Xiao Mian
# 好了 把它捣碎了就可以了
Ok. Just crush it
# 捣碎了之后它的香味就可以了
Crushing brings out the aroma
# 接下来最关键的步骤就把这
Next, the most important step
# 所有的调料把它组合在一起
is to combine all the ingredients
# 先调第一个麻酱 这是纯芝麻酱
First one, sesame sauce. Pure sesame sauce
# 纯芝麻酱有些太粘稠了
The pure sesame sauce is too thick
# 可以加一点点香油
You can dilute it with some sesame oil
# 这个的麻酱不能放太多
Don't add too much sesame sauce
# 太多的话汤它会太黏稠 糊的不清爽
Otherwise the soup would be too sticky. Not clear enough
# 就这样的小的勺子就一点点
Just a little bit with a small spoon like this
# 我们主要是起到一个增香的作用
Mainly to increase the aroma (of the dish)
# 第二个 猪油
Second, pork lard
# 这个也是加一勺就可以了 一小勺
Similarly, one small spoon would be enough
# 接下来姜和蒜放一点 个人所好
Then some ginger and garlic. Based on personal preference
# 接下来麻椒油
Next, green Sichuan peppercorn oil
# 我们只放这一调料勺就可以了
Just one spoon is enough
# 接下来放酱油
Then add some soy sauce
# 黄豆酱油一定要选对 不用太多
Must use the correct soy sauce, but not too much
# 接下来放这个辣椒 搅拌均匀了
Then the chili oil. Mix it well
# 这也是根据自己的 对根据个人口味
-This also depends on your personal taste. -Yep, as you like
# 还可以放点花椒油
Some red peppercorn oil
# 麻椒和花椒
Green peppercorn and red peppercorn #我查了一下，貌似麻椒指的是青花椒，花椒指的是红色的花椒
# 它的香味和麻味它是不一样的 来一点点
They have different aromas and numbing flavors. Add a little
# 好了这是小面的简单的基础的打料
Ok. That's the simple and basic ingredient of Xiao Mian
# 提前我们就把它打好的卤
Before adding the noodles
# 我们简单的先加一点点汤把它拌匀了
we add some hot water to mix it up
# 要搁点骨头汤就更香了
It'll be better if you use bone broth
# 锅已经开了
It's boiling
# 小面小面 他用的就是碱面
Xiao Mian, in particular, uses Jian Mian (noodles made with soda)
# 因为重庆和四川那边都喜欢吃这种碱面
Jian Mian is popular in Sichuan and Chongqing
# 其他地方没有这种面的话
If you can't buy such kind of noodle in your area
# 你买普通的手擀面条也可以
Just use common hand-made noodles
# 稍微细一点就可以了
It should be relatively thin
# 小面煮的时候不能时间长
Don't boil for too long
# 超过两分钟之后它的面会坨
The noodles will stick together if boiled over 2 minutes
# 这就是北京的话 锅挑儿
In Beijing, this is called 'Guo Tiaoer' (literally pick noodles out of the pot)
# 瞧瞧 这个还就是三两面
See? This is about 3 Liang (~ 150 g) of noodles
# 一会还有东西呢
We still need to add something later
# 炒好的肉末 芽菜 花生碎 葱花
Stir-fried minced meat, 'Ya Cai', minced peanut, minced green onion
# 豌豆可以打的时候带一点汤 为什么呢
When picking up the peas, you can scoop up some 'broth'. Why?
# 它本身压熟了 它会带一点甜味
Boiled peas give some sweetness by itself
# 非常香 看着就好
Very aromatic. It's already good from its look
# 这就是豌杂面 我拿走了大爷
-This is 'Wan Za Mian' (Xiao Mian with peas). -I'm taking this one, Da Ye
# 把面拌匀 尝尝这个小面味道怎么样
Mix the noodles well. Try and see how does it taste?
# 太好了 我们是类似于半干拌
Amazing. This is like 'semi-dried' noodles
# 汤汁没有那么多 油也没那么大
Not with much soup or much oil
# 不坨 利了
Not sticking together either
# 狼吞虎咽的
You are gobbling it up
# 你说香不香
Isn't it delicious?
# 这口感到嘴里边 各种复合味的香气
It feels in your mouth... All kinds of aroma
# 谁都不夺谁 谁都不抢谁
They are not fighting with or excluding each other
# 然后表现出来面条是恰到好处
Giving a perfect stage for the noodles
# 您过来看看大爷
Just come and have a look, Da Ye
# 这个带着汤太地道了 我不客气了大爷
This is so authentic with the 'soup'. I'll help myself
# 国辉
Guohui
# 真的不错
Good job!
# 大爷我跟你说
Da Ye, let me tell you
# 有一个网友叫
A fan named
# @你当我是浮夸吧
@你当我是浮夸吧
# 然后他问
He asked
# 想听
He wanted to know
# 大爷是怎么认识大妈的
How did you get to know Da Ma?
# 那时候我已经二十四五岁了
When I was about 24 to 25 years old
# 正好呢我一个舅舅
My uncle happend to be a colleague
# 跟我老伴她父亲是同事
of my wife's father
# 这一介绍呢
He introduced her to me
# 我一听说是干什么工作的呢
When I heard about her job
# 是做老师工作的
She was a teacher
# 我从小时候也尊重老师
I respected teachers when I was a kid
# 我又是老师的
I am a teacher's ...
# 自己家属
I am a teacher's family
# 我父亲就是老师
My father was a teacher
# 79年80年
In 1979 or 1980
# 那时候把老师看成是臭老9
At that time, teachers were regarded as bad guys
# 不受社会的敬重 爱戴
And were not respected in the society
# 这个职业呢也没人喜欢干
Nobody enjoyed that job then
# （大妈）当时挣36块钱
(Da Ma) earned 36 yuan each month
# 我41块5毛钱
For me, 41.5 yuan
# 但是我这个职业
However, my job
# 也不是一个好职业
was not a good one either
# 是吧
Right?
# 一个按过去的口头禅
Well in an old catchphrase
# 是个臭厨子 做饭的
I was just a poor cook, cooking for others
# 所以我们这两个职业
So our jobs...
# 说心里话
To be honest
# 当时不被人看重
were not respected at that time
# 搞对象确实有点难度
It was difficult for us to get married (to other people)
# 应该说比较门当户对
So we were a match
# 要讲究这个
If you consider the situation
# 所以当我舅舅把我带到他们家
So when my uncle introduced me to their family
# （大妈）对我还是挺满意的
(Da Ma) somehow was satisfied with me
# 一见钟情
Fell in love at first sight?
Fell in love at first sight.
# 但是我的岳母有点
But my mother-in-law was...
# 当时不太看好
not so happy then
# 觉得
Because she thought
# 是一厨师做饭的
I was just a cook
# 但是我这老伴
But my wife...
# 她有个奶奶
Her grandma was like
# 咱家姑娘
"Our girl, "
# 找一厨师好啊
" A chef was a perfect choice for her "
# 咱这姑娘也不会做饭
"She doesn't know how to cook"
# 找一厨师想做什么
"If she marries a chef,"
# 想吃什么
"then if there are something she want to have"
# 都能给会做
"(her husband) can make it for her."
# 厨师好 又顾家
"A chef is good, and can take care of the family."
# 这是给我一个评价
That's her evaluation of me.
# 找一个老师
(For me), marry a teacher
# 特别好在哪呢
is ideal. why?
# 第一
First
# 能正常班是吧
She has a regular working schedule
# 有寒暑假
She also has winter and summer vacations
# 另外以后真要说说有孩子了呢
What else, if we were going to have a kid
# 孩子放假她也放假
She would be on holiday if the kid was on holiday
# 孩子上学她也上学
She went to school when the kid started semester
# 就有人管
So the kid would be taken good care of
# 这家里头就比较完美
That would be a perfect condition for a family
# 所以我就同意了
So I was happy about this
# 那您第一次见大妈时候
What about your first impression on Da Ma
# 对她第一印象什么感觉
When you met her for the first time?
# 就是很小巧的一个老师
She was a slim girl, a teacher
# 是吧
Right?
# 说话也比较细声细语
She talked in a gentle tone
# 也是教语文的
And... she taught Chinese
# 是吧
Right?
# 我觉得
I thought...
# 还可以是吧
This was good, right?
# 我们就结合了
So we married
# 人家可对您一见钟情了
She fell in love with you immediately, after all
# 这样
Well
# 等我们接触以后
Later when we further contacted with each other
# 确实我们相处得非常好
We indeed went very well
# 是吧
Right?
# 到第二年我们又有了小孩
On the second year, we had a kid
# 确实体验了放寒暑假的时候
Indeed, we experienced the priority
# 这种优越
during winter and summer vacations
# 虽然工资低一点
Although our salaries were not high
# 但我们慢慢的去努力争取
We worked hard to pursue better life, slowly
# 去创造
to create more for the family
# 对日子就越来越过好了
And our life became better and better
# 这样
Well
# 在结婚的时候
When we were getting married
# 因为双方的家庭都比较相符
Since our families were similar
# 也没有过多的要什么彩礼
Her family did not ask me for a high bride price
# 我觉得这点挺宽容我的
I think they were lenient
# 而且应该说我们结婚也挺很平常
And to be honest, we had a normal wedding
# 也没有什么高档汽车
without exquisite cars
# 在北京我找了一个同学
I asked one of my classmates for help
# 同事给我借了一辆面包车
He lent me a van
# 送到西直门火车站
To send her to Xizhimen Railway Station
# 她还要坐一小时的火车
She had to take a train for an hour
# 到昌平南口
To Changping Nankou Station
# 那边我又找了一辆车
I rented another car
# 从火车站
at the railway station
# 又把她接到我们家里头
To pick her up to our family
# 没有隆重的婚礼
We did not have a grand wedding
# 也没有隆重的彩礼
nor a high bride price
# 但是我们很平平淡淡
But we did have a normal
# 办了十桌婚宴
wedding banquet of ten tables
# 这婚宴呢
The wedding banquet
# 那阵讲究在家里办
At that time, people tended to hold it at home
# 在家里办的还是挺隆重的
It was a solemn one
# 那菜都是谁做的
Who cooked the dishes?
# 您做的么
Was it you?
# 说到这儿我就特别感慨
For that part, I feel particularly emotional...